Mss.B.B445
American Philosophical Society
- Papers
  - Aabye, J. S., 1935 April - June (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Aabye, J. S.
    Three letters to Max Bergmann concerning the 50th anniversary of the Danish Forogsstationen. Invitation to attend declined.
  - Academic Friends of Hebrew University, 1941 February (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Academic Friends of the Hebrew University
    Circular concerning this organization and application forms.
  - Academic Press, Inc., 1942 December - 1944 May (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Academic Press, Inc.
    Publishers from New York. Max Bergmann thanks the company for complementary books recieved. Request from the company for information about a Dr. Feigl, who wrote a book they are about to publish.
  - Ace Glass Co., 1939 November - 1942 January (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Ace Glass Company
    Letters from Max Bergmann requesting catalogs. Includes invoices and estimates for apparatus.
  - Adams, Roger, 1934 March - 1942 July (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Adams, Roger
    Requests for reprints to and from Max Bergmann. Letter of recommendation for Sidney W. Fox from Adams.
  - Adkins, Homer, 1942 July - August (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Adkins, Homer
    A letter to Adkins from Max Bergmann requesting the suggestion of a "bright young chemist" for his lab.
  - Agfa Ansco Film Co., 1940 September - November (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Afga Films Company
    Correspondence between Max Bergmann and the Afga Ansco Photographic Materials department. Bergmann writes concerning prints which have wrongly been mailed.
  - Ahmad, Bashir, 1938 April (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Ahmad, Bashir
    A letter introducing Ahmad to Max Bergmann. A letter from Ahmad to Bergmann to make arrangements for a meeting.
  - Air Raid Preparations, 1943 March (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Air Raid Preparations
    Circular detailing what to do in case of air raids.
  - Akao, Akira, 1941 November (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Akao, Akira
    Request to Max Bergmann for reprints.
  - Alexander, Jerome, 1936 May - 1940 December (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Alexander, Jerome
    Mostly correspondence concerning reprints. Also request for a sample of fibrin, needed by Alexander for an experiment.
  - Alien Property Custodian, 1943 September - 1944 July (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Alien Property Custodian
    Circulars and application forms for membership. Organization was set up to provide reissues of foreign scientific articles which were not being distributed because of the War.
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, No. 1, 1943 August - 1944 October (Box 1, Folder 16)
    American Association for the Advancement of Science, No. 1-3
    Copies of the AAAS Bulletin from August, 1943-October, 1944.
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, No. 2, 1942 March - 1943 July (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Copies of the AAAS Bulletin form March, 1942-July, 1943. A list of the nominees for president of the AAAS for 1937.
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, No. 3, 1935 October - November (Box 1, Folder 18)
    A notice of Max Bergmann's election to the society.
  - American Chemical Society, No. 1, 1934 August - 1937 December (Box 1, Folder 19)
    American Chemical Society, No. 1-5
    Five folders ranging from 1934-1944. Notices of meetings for the Division of Organic Chemistry, the Division of Biological Chemistry, and the Division of Agricultural Chemistry. A note of congratulations to Max Bergmann for becoming a member of the ACS. Reprints from symposiums. Invitations to speak at various local sections.
  - American Chemical Society, No. 2, 1935 January - 1936 June (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - American Chemical Society, No. 3, 1934 August - 1944 January (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - American Chemical Society, No. 4, 1944 September (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - American Chemical Society, No. 5, 1941 September - 1944 April (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - American Chemical Society - Rochester Section, 1941 October - 1941 November (Box 2, Folder 1)
    ACS-Rochester Section
    Letters to and from Max Bergmann concerning expenses for a speech given to the Rochester section of the American Chemical Society.
  - American Leather Chemists Association, No. 1, 1943 June - 1944 August (Box 2, Folder 2)
    The American Leather Chemists Association, No. 1-3
    Three folders ranging from November, 1934-May, 1944. Membership application forms, notices of annual meetings, ballot sheets for electing members and officers, and voting on society policies. Copies of proceedings. Notes of thanks for speeches given.
  - American Leather Chemists Association, No. 2, 1937 August - 1942 August (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - American Leather Chemists Association, No. 3, 1934 May - 1940 April (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - American Men of Science, September 1937 - 1939 April (Box 2, Folder 5)
    American Men of Science
    A 1939 notice of scientists to be included in the 6th edition. Correspondence between Max Bergmann and J. McKeen Cattell regarding the "Biographical Directory of American Men of Science."
  - American Society of Biological Chemists, No. 1, 1934 April - 1937 December (Box 2, Folder 6)
    American Society of Biological Chemists, No. 1-3
    Three folders ranging from April, 1934- October, 1944. Notice of official meetings. Official ballot cards. Abstracts from meetings. Notice of membership.
  - American Society of Biologiccal Chemists, No. 2, 1942 January - 1944 June (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - American Society of Biological Chemists, No. 3, 1941 November - 1944 October (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Anderson, R. J., 1934 July - 1942 January (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Anderson, R.J.
    Letter of recommendation to Max Bergmann of Dr. M.S. Newman. A letter from Bergmann to Anderson asking if he knew of any "young chemists available to work in his lab."
  - Andrews, A. C., 1937 November- 1938 March (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Andrews, A.C.
    Requests for reprints to Max Bergmann.
  - Andrews, James C., 1934 October - 1940 November (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Andrews, James C.
  - Amino Acids (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Amino Acids
    Cross references to other files.
  - Anslow, William P., 1944 January (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Anslow, William P.
    Personal letter from Max Bergmann to Anslow.
  - Anson, Mortimer L., 1937 May - 1939 October (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Anson, Mortimer L.
    Correspondance between Max Bergmann and Mortimer Anson concerning the growth of crystals of carboxypeptidase.
  - Apparatus (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Apparatus
    Cross references to other files in the collection.
  - Applicants, No. 1, 1941 October - 1943 September (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Applicants, No. 1-2
    Applications for volunteer and paid positions in Max Bergmann's lab, from 1941-1944.
  - Applicants, No. 2, 1942 February - 1944 May (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Archives of Biochemistry, 1942 December - 1944 October (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Archives of Biochemistry
    Correspondence between Max Bergmann and the Archives of Biochemistry bewtween December, 1942 and October, 1944. All deal with reviewing or declining to review articles.
  - Armour Research Foundation, 1945 October (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Armour Research Foundation
    A request for chemical compounds for research.
  - Arnoldi, H., 1934 June (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Arnoldi, H.
    Correspondence between Max Bergmann and Arnoldi regarding advice on how to patent a new method Arnoldi has developed. The letter to Bergmann is typed in German.
  - Ascorbic Acid (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Ascorbic Acid
    Crossreferences to other files in the collection.
  - Asselbergs, H. B., 1939 March - April (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Asselbergs, H.B.
    Two letters between Max Bergmann and Asselbergs, from March and April, 1939. Asselbergs wrote to Bergman for advice on the best way to synthesize an ester. The letter to Bergmann is handwritten German.
  - Astbury, William T., 1935 September - 1939 April (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Astbury, William T.
    Correspondence between Max Bergman and William T. Astbury. Includes requests for reprints, discussion of Astbury's work on animal protein, and letters about reviewing each others work before publication.
  - Atlantic Gelatin Company, Inc., 1934 December - 1935 January (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Atlantic Gelatin Company, Inc.
    A letter requesting a recommendation for a German emigre chemist with expetise in the manufature of photographic geltain.
  - Axelrad, Felix, 1940 April - 1941 March (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Axelrad, Felix
    Correspondence requesting the aid of Max Bergmann in affairs pertaining to jobs and wartime internment. The letters from Axelrad to Bergmann are typed in German.
  - B - Misc., No. 1, 1935 October - 1944 October (Box 2, Folder 26)
    B-Misc., No. 1-5
    General miscellaneous material. Including: thanks for reprints, letters wanting donations, letters to make appointments, letters wanting Max Bergmann for a reference. Some ASBC info. Requests for exp. samples. Requests for Bergmann to nominate candidates for jobs if he knows anyone suitable (especially from the Leather Chem. Ind). Letter from Seigfried Bergmann interned in a POW camp in Canada, wants to know if he is related to Max Bergmann. Notice of Bergmann's inclusion in Biographical Encyclopedia of America.
  - B - Misc., No. 2, 1937 April - 1944 June (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - B - Misc., No. 3, 1939 March - 1942 August (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - B - Misc., No. 4, 1934 June - 1944 September (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - B - Misc., No. 5, 1938 June - 1942 November (Box 3, Folder 3)
    B-Misc., No.1-5
  - Bachmann, Werner E., 1942 July - 1944 March (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Bachmann, Werner E.
    Correspondence between max Bergmann and Werner E. Bachmann. Letters pertaining to matters of staffing positions in Bergmann's lab.
  - Baekeland, L. H., 1936 March - 1944 December (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Bakeland, L.H.
    Includes letters for reprints, recommendations of students, and a letter of condolence to Mrs. Bakeland.
  - Baker, Lillian E., 1940 August - 1944 September (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Baker, Lillian E.
    Several letters mainly about her illness, some professional notes about Max Bergmann wanting her to write a paper, also a request for references from Bergmann.
  - Baker Colloid 46, 1941 June - November (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Baker Colloid 46
    Correspondence from 1941 between Max Bergmann and Baker and Co., Inc. The letters are in regards to the use of a new chemical, "Baker Colloid 46," by Bergmann.
  - Ballentine, Robert, No. 1, 1941 August - 1944 September (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Ballentine, Robert, No. 1
    Correspondence regarding publication of his research 1941-43. Letters of recommendation, vita, application, interview, impressions of Max Bergmann.
  - Ballentine, Robert, No. 2, 1940 October - 1941 March (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Ballentine, Robert, No. 2
    Letters of recommendation, curriculum vitae, application, interview, impressions of Max Bergmann.
  - Barger, George, 1936 June (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Barger, George
    Four telegrams concerning chemical equation of pyrimidine, Vit B, June 1936.
  - Barschall, Hermann, 1943 June - September (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Barschall, Hermann
    Correspondence from Max Bergmann to various labs trying to get Barschall (German refugee) a job.
  - Barus, Maxwell, 1944 September - October (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Barus, Maxwell
    Requests to Max Bergmann for information regarding a legal case. Bergmann refers Barus to other scientists.
  - Bass, Lawrence W., 1936 April - May (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Bass, Lawrence W.
    Correspondence concerning a speech at the New York section of the American Chemical Society in 1936.
  - Beadle, George Wells, 1943 December (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Beadle, George Wells
    Correspondence concerning a sample of l-serine needed for an experiment.
  - Beard, Howard H., 1936 November - 1938 September (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Beard, Howard H.
    Letters regarding a paper and an experiment in which Beard seeks the advice of Bergmann.
  - Beard, Joseph W., 1941 September (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Beard, Joseph W.
    Correspondence between Max Bergmann and Joseph Beard concerning an experiment.
  - Berger, William V., 1943 December (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Berger, William V.
    Two letters from Max Bergmann to William Berger in regards to reprints and chemical samples for experiments.
  - Berggren, Ruth E. L., 1936 January - February (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Berggren, Ruth E. L.
    Letter seeking employment in Bergmann's lab.
  - Berliner, Arnold, 1935 November - 1940 May (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Berliner, Arnold
    Correspondence between Max Bergmann and Berliner regarding employment.
  - Bernheim, Frederick, 1937 April - 1940 September (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Bernheim, Frederick
    General correspondence. Letters include details about an experiment and also the fate of an English scientist working under war conditions.
  - Behrens, Otto K., 1938 December - 1944 September (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Behrens, Otto K.
    General correspondence between Max Bergmann and Otto K. Behrens. Included are letters regarding Behrens working in Bergmann's lab for one year.
  - Beiser, A., 1943 November (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Beiser, Arthur
    A copy of Beiser's curriculum vitae sent with a note to Max Bergmann.
  - Benton, Arthur F., 1942 January (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Benton, Arthur F.
    Correspondence regarding letters of recommendation for William Fenton Ross.
  - Bergmann, Max, No. 1, 1941 April - 1945 November (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Bergmann, Max, No. 1
    Includes: a list of reprints 1933-39, draft of a biographical sketch about Max Bergmann, written by Joseph S. Fruton for the American Academy of Science, mailing list for reprints, list of journals sent to Bergmann, and a list of membership to various societies.
  - Bergmann, Max, No. 2, 1941 January - 1944 March (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Bergmann, Max, No. 2
    Includes some personal and family correspondence. Also, a bibliography of Bergmann's articles, 1911-1925.
  - Bhagvat, Kamala A., 1939 Janaury - May (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Bhagvat, Kamala
    A note of thanks to Max Bergmann.
  - Biochemical Society, 1943 October - 1945 February (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Biochemical Society
    Notices of meetings, nomination forms, receipts for payments of dues, and an inquiry from Max Bergmann regarding the terms of membership.
  - Biological Abstracts, 1941 October - 1943 July (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Biological Abstracts
    Letters asking Max Bergmann to participate in abstracting articles.
  - Blackadder, T., 1934 July - 1943 June (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Blackadder, T.
    Letter from T. Blackadder (of Rohm and Hass Co.) to Max Bergmann, requesting samples of tanning materials.
  - Blank, Irvin H., 1934 June - 1936 August (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Blank, Irvin H.
    Notes of thanks to Max Bergmann regarding advice given.
  - Bloch, Henry S., 1939 June - 1941 March (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Bloch, Henry S.
    Correspondence regarding job advice from Max Bergmann. Included is a copy of Henry Bloch's curriculum vitae.
  - Bloch, Konrad, No. 1, 1941 May - 1943 October (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Bloch, Konrad, No. 1
    Corresondence between Max Bergmann and Konrad Bloch. Letters are in regards to advice on gaining citizenship in the United States and concerns over the state of work within the field of science.
  - Bloch, Konrad, No. 2, 1936 December - 1940 October (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Bloch, Konrad, No. 2
    Konrad Bloch's application to the "Relief and Research Fund Inc. N.Y." for a grant to do Ph.D. research under H.T. Clarke at Columbia University. Includes letters of recommendation from Max Bergmann.
  - Block, Richard J, 1937 February - 1943 March (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Block, Richard J.
    Correspondence between Richard J. Block and Max Bergmann. Includes letters requesting reprints, advice on chemical experiments, and a note requesting that Max Bergmann comment on a paper of Block's.
  - Blumenthal, Fritz, 1941 May (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Blumenthal, Fritz
    A letter informing Max Bergmann of Blumenthal's intentions to take the U.S. Medical Board examinations.
  - Boas, Franz, 1939 December - 1940 March (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Boas, Franz
    Correspondence between Franz Boas and Max Bergmann. Letters inform Bergmann of Boas intentions to set up a Palestine Science Society for Jewish Scientists in Europe. Includes a list of scholars with sympathy to the cause.
  - Bolton, E. K., 1934 May - 1935 May (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Bolton, E. K.
    Correspondence between E. K. Bolton (of DuPont Nemours Co.) and Max Bergmann. Included are requests for a sample of dyes for experimental purposes, and also a note congratulating Bergmann on his recent move to the Rockefeller Institute.
  - Book Order, 1941 November - 1944 September (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Book Order
    Miscellaneous material relating to book orders. Includes catalogs, book orders, and reciepts of payment.
  - Bookbinders, 1942 July - 1943 October (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Bookbinders
    Reciepts of payment to "Knoll's Bookbindery."
  - Borsook, H., 1941 September (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Borsook, H.
    Correspondence regarding a speech given by Borsook at the Rockefeller Institute on September 24, 1941.
  - Boston Hide & Leather Co., 1941 October - December (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Boston Hide and Leather Company
    Correspondence regarding the recommendation of a leather chemist.
  - Boyd, George Edward, 1941 October 18 - 1942 January 14 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Boyd, George Edward
    Letter requesting polypeptides for an experiment.
  - Brand, Erwin, 1934 July 15 - 1944 March 21 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Brand, Erwin
    Correspondence between Erwin Brand and Max Bergmann. Includes letters regarding the American Chemical Society, Brand's work, and also letters in regards to the exchange of both chemicals and equipment between Bergmann and Brand.
  - Brand, Hugo, 1935 September (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Brand, Hugo
    Correspondence regarding the employment for a German refugee leather chemist.
  - Braunschweig, Theodore, 1941 June - December (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Braunschweig, Theodore
    Correspondence regarding Braunschweig's application to the American Leather Chemist Association.
  - Brenner, Carl Max, 1940 January - April (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Brenner, Carl Max
    Correspondence regarding Brenner's appointment to work for one year in Max Bergmann's lab and the arrangements for his arrival.
  - British Association for the Advancement of Science, 1937 March - September (Box 4, Folder 10)
    British Association for the Advancement of Science
    Invitations to meetings.
  - Buchman, Edwin R., 1938 March - 1939 May (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Buchman, Edwin R.
    Correspondence regarding the presence of vitamin B in protein hydrolysate.
  - Bueding, Ernest, 1941 September - 1944 October (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Bueding, Ernest
    Miscellaneous correspondence between Ernest Bueding and Max Bergmann. Letters linclude request for papain to A. K. Balls and the recommendation of Bueding to th American Society of Biological Chemists.
  - C - Misc., No. 1, 1942 January - 1944 November (Box 4, Folder 13)
    C - Misc., No. 1
    Miscellaneous correspondence. Includes invitations to meetings, inquiries for chemicals, recommendation for a Bruno R. Roberts, short biographical sketch of Hermann J. Muller.
  - C - Misc., No. 2, 1934 September - 1940 November (Box 4, Folder 14)
    C- Misc., No. 2
    Miscellaneous correspondence. Includes a reference for Sydney W. Fox, notes of thanks to and from Max Bergmann regarding reprints. Letter on how to hydroginate carbobenzoxy compounds. Letter from Dr. Calvert, a Spanish war scientist and refugee, seeking help from Bergmann.
  - C - Misc., No. 3, 1934 September - 1940 November (Box 4, Folder 15)
    C - Misc., No. 3
    Miscellaneous correspondence. Includes a note from Chemical Publishing Co., a recommendation for Dora Stern to the Chemists Club of N.Y., and a note of thanks and recommendation of Calvin Gloumbic to Max Bergmann. Request for information on the manufacture and preparation of papain from a Dr. Chatelier. Notice of Bergmann's membership to the London Chemical Society. Invitation to the meeting of the Washington section of the American Chemical Society. A request for Bergmann to serve on a Protein Committee for NRC from William Clarke. A letter from the American Bureau for Medical Aid to China seeking medical supplies.
  - C - Misc., No. 4, 1941 January - 1944 May (Box 4, Folder 16)
    C - Misc., No. 4
    Miscellaneous correspondence. Includes addresses of agencies to aid refugees with names of administrators. Dinner invitations. A letter of recommendation of a Mrs. Marion Coomber written by Joseph Fruton. A copy of a letter to Albert Einstein from the "Coatwise Petroleum Company" regarding a reference given by Einstein and Max Bergmann.
  - C - Misc., No. 5, 1934 June - 1941 February (Box 4, Folder 17)
    C - Misc., No. 5
    Invitation to a symposium on "The Struggle for Economic Security in Democracy." Request to Max Bergmann for Chulmoogra seeds. Program for Temperature Symposium at Cornell University. Request for a catalouge of pyrex glassware. A letter of recommendation for Felix Heinemann.
  - C - Misc., No. 6, 1937 March - 1942 June (Box 4, Folder 18)
    C - Misc., No. 6
    Miscellaneous correspondence. Includes a request for a meeting to discuss o-nitrophenols from George Cronheim of G.F. Harvey Co., and a government job description for chief chemist and chemical engineer.
  - Cahnmann, Hans J, 1941 October - 1942 October (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Cahnmann, Hans J.
    Correspondence concerning employment for Chanmann. Letters from Cahnmann to Bergmann are in handwritten German.
  - Calvery, Herbert O, 1934 April - 1942 March (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Calvery, Herbert O.
    Informal letters concerning chemicals, job recommendations, and plans for Calvery's visit to New York.
  - Campbell, Editha C, 1934 May - 1940 May (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Campbell, Editha C.
    Correspondence between Max Bergmann and Editha C. Campbell (of the Publishing Division of the Rockefeller Institute), regarding where and how often to list and publish material.
  - Canadian Review of Biology, 1941 November - 1942 January (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Canadian Review of Biology
    Invitation for Max Bergmann to join the "Comite de Collaboration Scientifique."
  - Cannan, R. Keith, 1935 May - 1944 April (Box 4, Folder 23)
    Cannan, R. Keith
    Correspondence between R. Keith Cannan (President of the Harvey Society) and Max Bergmann. Letters include: the appointment of Bergmann to the Harvey Society, notes of congratulations, requests for reprints, notes concerning different chemicals, and a speech given by Bergmann.
  - Cantoni, Giulio, 1941 December - 1943 March (Box 4, Folder 24)
    Cantoni, Giulio
    Correspondence, between Max Bergmann and Italian refugee Giulio Cantoni, concerning his chances of employment in the United States. Included is Cantoni's curriculum vitae.
  - Carbide & Carbon Chemicals Corp., 1934 August - 1935 February (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Carbide & Carbon Chemicals Corp.
    Letters requesting chemicals. Receipts of purchase.
  - Carpenter, Samuel C., Jr., No. 1, 1935 October - 1940 October (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Carpenter, Samuel C., Jr., No. 1
    General correspondence pertaining to the employment of Samuel C. Carpenter Jr. Includes several letters of recommendation from Max Bergmann.
  - Carpenter, Samuel C., Jr., No. 2, 1941 February - 1943 December (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Carpenter, Samuel C., Jr., No. 2
    Personal correspondence.
  - Carter, Herbert E, 1941 May - 1943 February (Box 4, Folder 28)
    Carter, Herbert E.
    Letters requesting chemicals and reprints.
  - Carter, Neal M, 1941 January - 1944 October (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Carter, Neal M.
    General correspondence.
  - Catalogs, 1939 December (Box 4, Folder 30)
    Catalogs